<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-06-25T09:57:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Neeraj’s Blog</title><author><name>Neeraj</name></author><entry><title type="html">Complete Tutor Training Guide: Evidence-Based Learning Principles for Learn To Be Tutors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/21/complete-tutor-training-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Complete Tutor Training Guide: Evidence-Based Learning Principles for Learn To Be Tutors" /><published>2025-06-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/21/complete-tutor-training-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/21/complete-tutor-training-guide/"><![CDATA[<nav id="TOC" role="doc-toc">
  <a href="/">Home</a><br>
  <strong>Contents</strong><label for="contents">⊕</label>
  <input type="checkbox" id="contents">
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#automaticity-building-fluent-foundations"
  id="toc-automaticity-building-fluent-foundations">1. Automaticity:
  Building Fluent Foundations</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions"
  id="toc-how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions">How This
  Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#retrieval-practice-strengthening-memory-through-testing"
  id="toc-retrieval-practice-strengthening-memory-through-testing">2.
  Retrieval Practice: Strengthening Memory Through Testing</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-1"
  id="toc-how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-1">How This
  Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a
  href="#spaced-retrieval-practice-timing-for-long-term-retention"
  id="toc-spaced-retrieval-practice-timing-for-long-term-retention">3.
  Spaced Retrieval Practice: Timing for Long-Term Retention</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-2"
  id="toc-how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-2">How This
  Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#interleaving-mixing-practice-for-better-learning"
  id="toc-interleaving-mixing-practice-for-better-learning">4.
  Interleaving: Mixing Practice for Better Learning</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-3"
  id="toc-how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-3">How This
  Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#reducing-cognitive-load-managing-mental-resources"
  id="toc-reducing-cognitive-load-managing-mental-resources">5. Reducing
  Cognitive Load: Managing Mental Resources</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-4"
  id="toc-how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-4">How This
  Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#i-do-we-do-you-do-the-gradual-release-model"
  id="toc-i-do-we-do-you-do-the-gradual-release-model">6. “I Do, We Do,
  You Do”: The Gradual Release Model</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-5"
  id="toc-how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-5">How This
  Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#putting-it-all-together-a-complete-learn-to-be-session"
  id="toc-putting-it-all-together-a-complete-learn-to-be-session">Putting
  It All Together: A Complete Learn To Be Session</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
  </ul>
</nav>

<main>
<p>Welcome to the complete Learn To Be tutor training guide. This
comprehensive resource covers the six core evidence-based learning
principles that every effective tutor should understand and apply. Each
principle is backed by cognitive science research and includes specific
guidance on how to implement it during your tutoring sessions.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="automaticity-building-fluent-foundations">1. Automaticity:
Building Fluent Foundations</h2>
<p><strong>What it is:</strong> Automaticity is the ability to perform
skills so fluently that they require minimal conscious attention,
freeing up working memory for higher-order thinking.</p>
<p><strong>The Science:</strong> When students haven’t developed
automaticity in foundational skills, their limited working memory gets
consumed by basic operations, leaving no mental space for
problem-solving or creativity.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more:</strong> <a
href="https://www.justinmath.com/cognitive-science-of-learning-developing-automaticity/">Cognitive
Science of Learning: Developing Automaticity</a></p>
<h3 id="how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions">How This
Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</h3>
<p><strong>Before moving to new concepts:</strong> - Assess which
foundational skills need strengthening (math facts, sight words, etc.) -
Use quick fluency checks: “Let’s do some rapid-fire multiplication
tables before we tackle word problems”</p>
<p><strong>During practice:</strong> - Set both accuracy AND speed
goals: “Let’s aim to get these addition facts correct in under 3 seconds
each” - Use timed drills, but keep them short and engaging - Celebrate
when students achieve automatic recall</p>
<p><strong>Maintaining automaticity:</strong> - Start each session with
2-3 minutes of foundational skill practice - Regularly revisit
previously mastered skills to prevent decay - Connect automatic skills
to new learning: “Since you know your times tables automatically, you
can focus on the problem-solving strategy here”</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="retrieval-practice-strengthening-memory-through-testing">2.
Retrieval Practice: Strengthening Memory Through Testing</h2>
<p><strong>What it is:</strong> Retrieval practice involves recalling
information from memory rather than simply re-reading or reviewing
notes. The act of retrieval itself strengthens memory.</p>
<p><strong>The Science:</strong> Testing isn’t just for assessment—it’s
one of the most powerful learning tools. Students remember information
better when they practice pulling it out of their memory.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more:</strong> <a
href="https://pdf.retrievalpractice.org/RetrievalPracticeGuide.pdf">Retrieval
Practice Guide</a></p>
<h3 id="how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-1">How This
Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</h3>
<p><strong>Start each session with retrieval:</strong> - “Before we
learn something new, let’s see what you remember from last time” - Ask
specific questions about previous concepts without giving hints first -
Use mini-quizzes or flashcards for key facts and procedures</p>
<p><strong>During learning:</strong> - After explaining a concept, close
your notes and ask the student to explain it back - Use the “blank page”
technique: have students write down everything they remember about a
topic - Ask “How did you solve that?” to make students retrieve their
thinking process</p>
<p><strong>End sessions with retrieval:</strong> - “Let’s review what we
covered today without looking at our notes” - Give students 2-3 practice
problems that require them to recall the day’s learning - Assign
retrieval-based homework: “Tomorrow, try to solve these problems before
reviewing your notes”</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="spaced-retrieval-practice-timing-for-long-term-retention">3.
Spaced Retrieval Practice: Timing for Long-Term Retention</h2>
<p><strong>What it is:</strong> Spacing out retrieval practice over time
(rather than massing it in one session) dramatically improves long-term
retention.</p>
<p><strong>The Science:</strong> Information reviewed at increasing
intervals becomes more deeply embedded in long-term memory. The slight
forgetting that occurs between sessions actually strengthens memory when
information is successfully retrieved.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more:</strong> <a
href="https://pdf.retrievalpractice.org/SpacingGuide.pdf">Spacing
Guide</a></p>
<h3 id="how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-2">How This
Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</h3>
<p><strong>Plan your review schedule:</strong> - Review new concepts the
next session, then again after a week, then after two weeks - Keep a
simple tracking system of what needs to be reviewed when - Don’t abandon
topics once “mastered”—schedule periodic check-ins</p>
<p><strong>Structure your sessions:</strong> - Spend the first 10
minutes reviewing concepts from 1-2 sessions ago - Include a few
problems from several sessions back - Mix recent and older material
throughout the session</p>
<p><strong>Communicate with students:</strong> - Explain why you’re
reviewing “old” material: “We’re not going backwards—we’re making sure
this sticks in your long-term memory” - Help students see the connection
between spaced practice and their improved performance over time</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="interleaving-mixing-practice-for-better-learning">4.
Interleaving: Mixing Practice for Better Learning</h2>
<p><strong>What it is:</strong> Interleaving involves mixing different
types of problems or concepts within a single practice session, rather
than practicing one type at a time (blocking).</p>
<p><strong>The Science:</strong> While blocking feels easier and shows
faster initial improvement, interleaving leads to better long-term
retention and improved ability to discriminate between different problem
types.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more:</strong> <a
href="https://www.retrievalpractice.org/interleaving">Interleaving</a></p>
<h3 id="how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-3">How This
Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</h3>
<p><strong>Mix problem types:</strong> - Instead of doing 10 addition
problems, then 10 subtraction problems, alternate: addition,
subtraction, addition, multiplication, subtraction - For reading:
alternate between different comprehension strategies within one passage
- For writing: practice different sentence types within one
paragraph</p>
<p><strong>Interleave concepts across sessions:</strong> - Don’t finish
one topic completely before starting another - Return to previous topics
while introducing new ones - Create problem sets that require students
to identify which strategy to use</p>
<p><strong>Help students with the difficulty:</strong> - Warn students
that interleaved practice feels harder initially: “This might feel more
challenging, but it’s helping your brain learn better” - Emphasize the
discrimination skill: “Part of learning math is knowing which type of
problem you’re looking at” - Celebrate when students correctly identify
problem types: “Great! You recognized this was a proportion problem”</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="reducing-cognitive-load-managing-mental-resources">5. Reducing
Cognitive Load: Managing Mental Resources</h2>
<p><strong>What it is:</strong> Cognitive load theory recognizes that
our working memory is limited. Effective instruction minimizes
unnecessary mental burden so students can focus on learning.</p>
<p><strong>The Science:</strong> Students can only process a limited
amount of information at once. When cognitive load is too high, learning
suffers. We must carefully manage what we ask students to think about
simultaneously.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more:</strong> <a
href="https://www.justinmath.com/cognitive-science-of-learning-minimizing-cognitive-load/">Cognitive
Science of Learning: Minimizing Cognitive Load</a></p>
<h3 id="how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-4">How This
Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</h3>
<p><strong>Break concepts into small chunks:</strong> - Introduce one
new idea at a time - Master each component before combining them - Use
the “bite-sized lessons” approach: focus on single concepts per
session</p>
<p><strong>Reduce extraneous load:</strong> - Minimize distractions in
your tutoring environment - Use clear, simple language - Avoid
introducing multiple new terms simultaneously - Keep examples focused on
the core concept</p>
<p><strong>Support working memory:</strong> - Provide reference sheets
for formulas or steps - Use visual aids and diagrams - Allow students to
write down intermediate steps - Don’t rush—give time for processing</p>
<p><strong>Gradually increase complexity:</strong> - Start with the
simplest version of a concept - Add complexity only after the basics are
solid - Remove supports (like reference sheets) gradually as
automaticity develops</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="i-do-we-do-you-do-the-gradual-release-model">6. “I Do, We Do,
You Do”: The Gradual Release Model</h2>
<p><strong>What it is:</strong> A structured approach to instruction
where the tutor first models a skill (I Do), then works through examples
with the student (We Do), and finally has the student practice
independently (You Do).</p>
<p><strong>The Science:</strong> This gradual release of responsibility
allows students to build confidence and competence systematically. It
provides scaffolding that’s removed as students become more capable.</p>
<h3 id="how-this-applies-to-learn-to-be-tutoring-sessions-5">How This
Applies to Learn To Be Tutoring Sessions</h3>
<p><strong>“I Do” - Modeling (5-10 minutes):</strong> - Demonstrate the
complete process while thinking aloud - Keep your example simple and
focused on the core concept - Explain your reasoning: “I’m doing this
because…” - Don’t ask questions yet—just show the complete process -
Example: “I’m going to show you how to solve this fraction addition
problem. First, I need to find a common denominator…”</p>
<p><strong>“We Do” - Guided Practice (10-15 minutes):</strong> - Work
through 2-3 examples together - Start by doing most of the work,
gradually shifting responsibility to the student - Ask guiding
questions: “What should we do first?” “Why did we choose that
denominator?” - Provide immediate feedback and correction - Let students
make mistakes and guide them to self-correction - Example: “Now let’s
try one together. You tell me what the first step should be…”</p>
<p><strong>“You Do” - Independent Practice (15-20 minutes):</strong> -
Have students work through problems independently - Resist the urge to
jump in immediately when they struggle - Provide hints rather than
answers: “Look back at what we did in the first step” - Observe their
process, not just their answers - Celebrate both correct processes and
correct answers - Example: “Now try these three problems on your own.
I’ll be here if you get stuck, but see how much you can do
independently.”</p>
<p><strong>Key principles for all three phases:</strong> - Keep
cognitive load manageable—focus on one small concept at a time - Move
between phases based on student understanding, not a rigid timeline -
Some students may need more “We Do” time before moving to “You Do” -
Return to earlier phases if students struggle during independent
practice</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="putting-it-all-together-a-complete-learn-to-be-session">Putting
It All Together: A Complete Learn To Be Session</h2>
<p>Here’s how these six principles work together in a typical 45-60
minute tutoring session:</p>
<p><strong>Opening (5 minutes):</strong> - <strong>Retrieval
practice:</strong> Quick review of concepts from previous sessions -
<strong>Spaced practice:</strong> Include problems from 1-2 weeks ago -
<strong>Automaticity:</strong> Brief drill of foundational skills</p>
<p><strong>Main instruction (25-35 minutes):</strong> -
<strong>Cognitive load:</strong> Introduce one new concept using
bite-sized chunks - <strong>I Do, We Do, You Do:</strong> Systematic
progression through the new material - <strong>Interleaving:</strong>
Mix the new concept with previously learned material</p>
<p><strong>Closing (5-10 minutes):</strong> - <strong>Retrieval
practice:</strong> Have student explain what they learned without notes
- <strong>Spaced practice:</strong> Assign problems that will be
reviewed in future sessions - <strong>Automaticity:</strong> Quick
practice of skills that need to become automatic</p>
<p><strong>Between sessions:</strong> - Plan which concepts need spaced
review - Prepare interleaved problem sets - Identify foundational skills
that need automaticity work</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>These six evidence-based principles form the foundation of effective
tutoring at Learn To Be. By understanding and applying automaticity,
retrieval practice, spaced practice, interleaving, cognitive load
management, and the gradual release model, you’ll help students not just
improve their grades, but develop deep, lasting understanding.</p>
<p>Remember: these principles work together. You don’t need to choose
between them—the most effective tutoring sessions incorporate all six
principles in a seamless, student-centered approach.</p>
<p>The goal isn’t just to help students with their immediate homework or
test preparation. It’s to teach them how to learn effectively, building
skills and confidence that will serve them throughout their academic
journey and beyond.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>This guide represents the core of Learn To Be’s evidence-based
tutoring approach. For questions or additional resources, contact us at
<a href="https://www.learntobe.org">Learn To Be</a>.</em></p>
</main>]]></content><author><name>Neeraj</name></author><category term="science-of-learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[← Return home Welcome to the complete Learn To Be tutor training guide. This comprehensive resource covers the six core evidence-based learning principles that every effective tutor should understand and apply. Each principle is backed by cognitive science research and includes specific guidance on how to implement it during your tutoring sessions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Automaticity: The Foundation of Higher-Order Learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/20/automaticity-the-foundation-of-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Automaticity: The Foundation of Higher-Order Learning" /><published>2025-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/20/automaticity-the-foundation-of-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/20/automaticity-the-foundation-of-learning/"><![CDATA[<nav id="TOC" role="doc-toc">
  <a href="/">Home</a><br>
  <strong>Contents</strong><label for="contents">⊕</label>
  <input type="checkbox" id="contents">
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#what-is-automaticity" id="toc-what-is-automaticity">What
  is Automaticity?</a></li>
  <li><a href="#why-automaticity-matters-for-academic-success"
  id="toc-why-automaticity-matters-for-academic-success">Why
  Automaticity Matters for Academic Success</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#the-math-example" id="toc-the-math-example">The Math
  Example</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#why-kids-struggle-in-math-and-other-subjects"
  id="toc-why-kids-struggle-in-math-and-other-subjects">Why Kids
  Struggle in Math (And Other Subjects)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-learn-to-be-approach-practice-practice-practice"
  id="toc-the-learn-to-be-approach-practice-practice-practice">The Learn
  To Be Approach: Practice, Practice, Practice</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#what-this-looks-like-in-practice"
  id="toc-what-this-looks-like-in-practice">What This Looks Like in
  Practice</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#the-broader-implications"
  id="toc-the-broader-implications">The Broader Implications</a></li>
  <li><a href="#building-automaticity-key-principles"
  id="toc-building-automaticity-key-principles">Building Automaticity:
  Key Principles</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#identify-the-true-fundamentals"
  id="toc-identify-the-true-fundamentals">1. Identify the True
  Fundamentals</a></li>
  <li><a href="#practice-to-fluency-not-just-accuracy"
  id="toc-practice-to-fluency-not-just-accuracy">2. Practice to Fluency,
  Not Just Accuracy</a></li>
  <li><a href="#use-distributed-practice"
  id="toc-use-distributed-practice">3. Use Distributed Practice</a></li>
  <li><a href="#make-it-engaging" id="toc-make-it-engaging">4. Make It
  Engaging</a></li>
  <li><a href="#monitor-and-maintain" id="toc-monitor-and-maintain">5.
  Monitor and Maintain</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#the-long-term-payoff" id="toc-the-long-term-payoff">The
  Long-Term Payoff</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
  </ul>
</nav>

<main>
<p>Automaticity might be one of the most important concepts in the
science of learning that most people have never heard of. Yet it’s the
invisible foundation that determines whether a student will struggle or
soar in their academic journey.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-automaticity">What is Automaticity?</h2>
<p>Automaticity is the ability to perform a skill so fluently and
effortlessly that it requires minimal conscious attention. When
something becomes automatic, your brain can execute it while
simultaneously focusing on higher-order thinking.</p>
<p>Think about driving a car. When you first learned, you had to
consciously think about every action: checking mirrors, signaling,
steering, braking. Your working memory was completely occupied with
these basic operations. But once driving became automatic, you could
navigate while having a conversation, listening to music, or planning
your day.</p>
<p>The same principle applies to learning.</p>
<h2 id="why-automaticity-matters-for-academic-success">Why Automaticity
Matters for Academic Success</h2>
<p>Here’s the crucial insight: <strong>our working memory is severely
limited</strong>. Cognitive scientists tell us we can only hold about
4-7 pieces of information in our conscious awareness at any given time.
This creates a fundamental bottleneck in learning.</p>
<p>When students haven’t developed automaticity in foundational skills,
their limited working memory gets consumed by basic operations, leaving
no mental space for higher-order thinking, problem-solving, or
creativity.</p>
<h3 id="the-math-example">The Math Example</h3>
<p>Consider a middle school student trying to solve this word
problem:</p>
<p><em>“Sarah has 3/4 of a pizza. She eats 1/6 of the whole pizza. How
much pizza does she have left?”</em></p>
<p>A student without automatic recall of fraction operations must use
their working memory to: - Remember how to find common denominators -
Recall the steps for subtracting fractions - Convert between mixed
numbers and improper fractions - Keep track of the problem context</p>
<p>By the time they’ve worked through the mechanical steps, they’ve
often lost sight of what the problem was actually asking. Their working
memory was hijacked by computational procedures that should have been
automatic.</p>
<p>In contrast, a student with automatic fraction skills can immediately
focus on the problem-solving strategy, the reasonableness of their
answer, and the mathematical relationships at play.</p>
<h2 id="why-kids-struggle-in-math-and-other-subjects">Why Kids Struggle
in Math (And Other Subjects)</h2>
<p>This is exactly why so many students hit a wall in mathematics around
middle school. Elementary math focuses heavily on building computational
fluency, but many students never achieve true automaticity with basic
facts and procedures.</p>
<p>When they encounter algebra, geometry, or more complex
problem-solving, they’re trying to learn new concepts while
simultaneously wrestling with arithmetic that should be effortless. It’s
like trying to write poetry while still sounding out individual
letters.</p>
<p>The same pattern appears across subjects: - <strong>Reading
comprehension</strong> suffers when students haven’t automated word
recognition - <strong>Writing</strong> becomes laborious when spelling
and grammar aren’t automatic - <strong>Science</strong> problem-solving
stalls when mathematical operations require conscious effort</p>
<h2 id="the-learn-to-be-approach-practice-practice-practice">The Learn
To Be Approach: Practice, Practice, Practice</h2>
<p>This is why at <a href="https://www.learntobe.org">Learn To Be</a>,
we emphasize practicing fundamentals until they become second nature.
We’re not being old-fashioned or drill-obsessed—we’re following what
cognitive science tells us about how learning actually works.</p>
<p>Our tutors understand that:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Fluency comes before complexity</strong>: Students need
automatic recall of math facts before tackling multi-step problems</li>
<li><strong>Repetition builds neural pathways</strong>: The brain
literally rewires itself through deliberate practice</li>
<li><strong>Speed matters</strong>: True automaticity means both
accuracy AND speed</li>
<li><strong>Regular review prevents decay</strong>: Skills that aren’t
maintained will lose their automatic quality</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="what-this-looks-like-in-practice">What This Looks Like in
Practice</h3>
<p>When our tutors work with students, they:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Assess automaticity gaps</strong>: Before moving to new
concepts, we identify which foundational skills need strengthening</li>
<li><strong>Use spaced repetition</strong>: We revisit basic skills
regularly to maintain automaticity</li>
<li><strong>Set fluency benchmarks</strong>: Students practice until
they can perform skills quickly and accurately</li>
<li><strong>Connect basics to bigger picture</strong>: We help students
see how automatic skills enable more interesting problem-solving</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-broader-implications">The Broader Implications</h2>
<p>Automaticity isn’t just about academic subjects—it’s about how
expertise develops in any domain. Musicians practice scales until
they’re automatic so they can focus on musical expression. Athletes
drill fundamental movements so they can react instinctively in
competition. Surgeons practice basic procedures until they become second
nature, freeing their minds to handle unexpected complications.</p>
<p>The pattern is universal: <strong>automaticity in fundamentals
enables excellence in advanced skills</strong>.</p>
<h2 id="building-automaticity-key-principles">Building Automaticity: Key
Principles</h2>
<p>If you’re a parent, teacher, or tutor, here are the key principles
for building automaticity:</p>
<h3 id="identify-the-true-fundamentals">1. Identify the True
Fundamentals</h3>
<p>Not everything needs to be automatic, but certain foundational skills
absolutely must be. In math, this includes: - Single-digit addition and
subtraction facts - Multiplication tables through 12x12 - Basic fraction
operations - Place value concepts</p>
<h3 id="practice-to-fluency-not-just-accuracy">2. Practice to Fluency,
Not Just Accuracy</h3>
<p>A student who can eventually get the right answer isn’t the same as a
student who can quickly and effortlessly get the right answer. Aim for
both speed and accuracy.</p>
<h3 id="use-distributed-practice">3. Use Distributed Practice</h3>
<p>Short, frequent practice sessions are more effective than long,
infrequent ones. Ten minutes of daily practice beats an hour once a
week.</p>
<h3 id="make-it-engaging">4. Make It Engaging</h3>
<p>Automaticity requires repetition, but repetition doesn’t have to be
boring. Use games, competitions, and varied formats to maintain
motivation.</p>
<h3 id="monitor-and-maintain">5. Monitor and Maintain</h3>
<p>Automaticity can decay without use. Regularly revisit foundational
skills even as students advance to new topics.</p>
<h2 id="the-long-term-payoff">The Long-Term Payoff</h2>
<p>Students who develop strong automaticity in foundational skills
experience a cascade of benefits:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Increased confidence</strong>: Success becomes more
predictable when basics are solid</li>
<li><strong>Better problem-solving</strong>: Mental resources are freed
up for strategic thinking</li>
<li><strong>Faster learning</strong>: New concepts build more easily on
automatic foundations</li>
<li><strong>Reduced anxiety</strong>: Students feel more in control when
they’re not struggling with basics</li>
<li><strong>Greater enjoyment</strong>: Learning becomes more engaging
when cognitive load is manageable</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Automaticity might not be the most exciting topic in education, but
it’s arguably the most important. It’s the difference between students
who struggle and students who thrive, between those who see learning as
a burden and those who see it as an adventure.</p>
<p>At Learn To Be, we’ve seen countless students transform when they
finally achieve automaticity in foundational skills. Suddenly, math
makes sense. Reading becomes enjoyable. Learning accelerates.</p>
<p>The path to academic excellence doesn’t start with advanced concepts
or creative projects—it starts with making the basics so automatic that
students’ minds are free to soar.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>Want to learn more about evidence-based tutoring approaches?
Check out our other posts in the <a
href="/2025/06/08/tutor-training-part-1/">tutor training series</a> or
reach out to us at <a href="https://www.learntobe.org">Learn To
Be</a>.</em></p>
</main>]]></content><author><name>Neeraj</name></author><category term="science-of-learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[← Return home Automaticity might be one of the most important concepts in the science of learning that most people have never heard of. Yet it’s the invisible foundation that determines whether a student will struggle or soar in their academic journey.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tutor Training Part 2 - How To Structure A Tutoring Session</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/09/tutor-training-part-2-how-to-structure-a-tutoring-session/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tutor Training Part 2 - How To Structure A Tutoring Session" /><published>2025-06-09T13:55:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T13:55:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/09/tutor-training-part-2-how-to-structure-a-tutoring-session</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/09/tutor-training-part-2-how-to-structure-a-tutoring-session/"><![CDATA[<nav id="TOC" role="doc-toc">
  <a href="/">Home</a><br>
  <strong>Contents</strong><label for="contents">⊕</label>
  <input type="checkbox" id="contents">
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#plan-bite-sized-lessons-ahead-of-time"
  id="toc-plan-bite-sized-lessons-ahead-of-time">Plan bite-sized lessons
  ahead of time</a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#ok-but-how-do-you-actually-create-a-bite-sized-lesson"
  id="toc-ok-but-how-do-you-actually-create-a-bite-sized-lesson">Ok but
  how do you actually create a bite-sized lesson?</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  </ul>
</nav>

<main>
<p>I will assume this isn’t your first session. Check out this post on
how to structure your first tutoring session.</p>
<p>Here are the steps to structure a tutoring session:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Plan bite-sized lessons ahead of time.</li>
<li>Do some retrieval practice from the previous session.</li>
<li>Use your lessons to do “I do, we do, you do”</li>
<li>Do some retrieval practice from the current session.</li>
</ol>
<p>Let’s go through these steps in detail.</p>
<h2 id="plan-bite-sized-lessons-ahead-of-time">Plan bite-sized lessons
ahead of time</h2>
<p>It’s important that the lessons you plan are bite-sized. This means
that you should plan to cover one or two concepts in each lesson. This
will make it easier for the student to understand and remember the
material.</p>
<p>For example, let’s say your student is learning about adding
fractions. There are a lot of ways to practice. For example, you could
create a single lesson that has problems like this:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><span class="math inline">\frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{4} =
?</span></p></li>
<li><p><span class="math inline">\frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{2} =
?</span></p></li>
<li><p><span class="math inline">\frac{3}{4} + \frac{1}{5} =
?</span></p></li>
<li><p><span class="math inline">\frac{7}{5} + \frac{1}{6} =
?</span></p></li>
</ol>
<p>What would be the issue if we just had one lesson with these
problems? And could we break this lesson into two smaller lessons?</p>
<p>Yes! I think there could be many lessons created from this: 1. Adding
fractions with the same denominator 2. Adding fractions with different
denominators 3. Adding mixed numbers 4. Adding improper fractions 5.
Adding fractions that need to be reduced</p>
<h3 id="ok-but-how-do-you-actually-create-a-bite-sized-lesson">Ok but
how do you actually create a bite-sized lesson?</h3>
<p>You can structure a lesson in the following way:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>A tutorial of sorts. This could be some written text or a video or
just a conversation. The goal is to explain the single concept.</li>
<li>A few examples on that topic.</li>
<li>7-10 problems on that topic.</li>
</ol>
</main>]]></content><author><name>Neeraj</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[← Return home I will assume this isn’t your first session. Check out this post on how to structure your first tutoring session.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tutor Training Part 1 - The myths of learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/08/tutor-training-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tutor Training Part 1 - The myths of learning" /><published>2025-06-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-06-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/06/08/tutor-training-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/06/08/tutor-training-part-1/"><![CDATA[<nav id="TOC" role="doc-toc">
  <a href="/">Home</a><br>
  <strong>Contents</strong><label for="contents">⊕</label>
  <input type="checkbox" id="contents">
  <ul>
  <li><a
  href="#myth-1-students-learn-better-when-taught-in-their-preferred-learning-style."
  id="toc-myth-1-students-learn-better-when-taught-in-their-preferred-learning-style.">Myth
  1: “Student’s learn better when taught in their preferred learning
  style.”</a></li>
  <li><a href="#myth-2-kids-learn-at-the-same-pace"
  id="toc-myth-2-kids-learn-at-the-same-pace">Myth 2: “Kids learn at the
  same pace”</a></li>
  <li><a href="#myth-3-learning-should-feel-easy"
  id="toc-myth-3-learning-should-feel-easy">Myth 3: “Learning should
  feel easy”</a></li>
  <li><a href="#myth-4-highlight-reread-cram-good-study-habits"
  id="toc-myth-4-highlight-reread-cram-good-study-habits">Myth 4:
  “Highlight, reread, cram = good study habits”</a></li>
  <li><a href="#myth-5-fun-learning" id="toc-myth-5-fun-learning">Myth
  5: “Fun = learning”</a></li>
  <li><a href="#myth-6-discovery-learning-works-for-novices"
  id="toc-myth-6-discovery-learning-works-for-novices">Myth 6:
  “Discovery learning works for novices”</a></li>
  </ul>
</nav>

<main>
<p>Before we dive into how to teach most effectively, we have to get rid
of some myths. If you’re a tutor at Learn To Be, you need to know
these.</p>
<h2
id="myth-1-students-learn-better-when-taught-in-their-preferred-learning-style.">Myth
1: “Student’s learn better when taught in their preferred learning
style.”</h2>
<p>This is one that has become so deeply ingrained in our heads but we
need to stop. If you’re a tutor at Learn To Be, you have to know this
one: there is no evidence that students have different learning styles.
Students who say they’re visual learners vs oral learners vs
kinaesthetic learners do not learn better when taught in their preferred
mode.</p>
<p>What IS true is that some material is better in certain ways. For
example, if you’re teaching geometry, you should use diagrams. If you’re
teaching phonics, you should use sound. If you’re teaching history, you
might just use words. Or you might use diagrams.</p>
<p>But regardless of the content, there is no evidence that students
learn better when taught in their preferred mode.</p>
<p><em>What happens if a parent or student says they are a visual
learner?</em> Listen to them, no need to tell them otehrwise. But use
what’s taught in this tutor training to teach according to the
content.</p>
<p>If you want to learn more learning styles, check out this <a
href="https://www.justinmath.com/people-differ-in-learning-speed-not-learning-style/">article
by Justin Skycak</a>.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="myth-2-kids-learn-at-the-same-pace">Myth 2: “Kids learn at the
same pace”</h2>
<p>Almost every kid has a huge ceiling on their potential. But some will
have to work harder to get there. You might be tutoring two kids in
their times tables. One kid seems to be memorizing them faster than the
other. And that’s ok. That will be the case. Some people learn faster
than others.</p>
<p>As a tutor, it will be up to you to keep the student who is learning
a little bit slower motivated. We’ll talk more about how to do that in
this tutor training.</p>
<p>If you want to learn more learning styles and learning speeds, check
out this <a
href="https://www.justinmath.com/people-differ-in-learning-speed-not-learning-style/">article
by Justin Skycak</a>.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="myth-3-learning-should-feel-easy">Myth 3: “Learning should feel
easy”</h2>
<p>It’s actually the opposite! Learning should feel hard. When you’re
asked a question, how you know you’ve learned it is if you can tease it
out of your brain. And in the early stages of learning something, that
can be hard.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="myth-4-highlight-reread-cram-good-study-habits">Myth 4:
“Highlight, reread, cram = good study habits”</h2>
<p>If you want to get an A on a test that’s coming up in a few days,
then <em>maybe</em> highlighting, rereading, and cramming will work. But
if you want to learn something for the long term, then this will never,
ever work.</p>
<p>For long term learning, it’s actually important to study something
and then put it away and come back to it later (maybe a day or two
later) and then test yourself on it. This is called “spaced
repetition”.</p>
<p>You space out your learning. So, for example, let’s say you learn a
new random fact like “the capital of Canada is Ottawa.” What you
traditionally have been told to do is to make a flashcard or something
and just drill this fact over and over again.</p>
<p>But if you’re smart about it, you’ll read this fact for a couple of
minutes and then put it away. And then come back to it a day or two
later and test yourself on it. You’ll see if you can pull it out of your
brain. Maybe the first time you look at it again, you won’t remember and
you’ll have to look at the answer. You study a little bit more. And then
you put it away again. And then you come back to it a day or two later
and test yourself on it again. And you keep doing this. Eventually, this
will be committed to your long term memory.</p>
<p>That’s what we mean by “spaced” in spaced repetition. You’re spacing
your studying out.</p>
<p>If you want to learn more about this idea of spaced repetition, check
out this <a
href="https://www.justinmath.com/spaced-repetition-is-more-than-memorization-its-also-generalization/">article
by Justin Skycak</a>.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="myth-5-fun-learning">Myth 5: “Fun = learning”</h2>
<p>Engagement helps <strong>attention</strong>, but students can be
engrossed in an activity while thinking about the wrong
thing—speed-typing answers into Kahoot, for instance. Learning only
sticks when their working memory grapples with the <em>meaningful</em>
element of the task.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="myth-6-discovery-learning-works-for-novices">Myth 6: “Discovery
learning works for novices”</h2>
<p>This will be less relevant to you as a tutor, but it’s still
important to know. Some people think that students learn better when
they “discover” things on their own. But this is not true. Students
learn better when they are taught directly. This is called “direct
instruction”. You teach the child directly what they need to know. One
way in which you can do this is via the “I do, we do, you do”
method.</p>
<hr />
</main>]]></content><author><name>Neeraj</name></author><category term="science-of-learning" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[← Return home Before we dive into how to teach most effectively, we have to get rid of some myths. If you’re a tutor at Learn To Be, you need to know these.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I Brought My LDL (“Bad”) Cholesterol Down 70 Points in 3 Months</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/06/ldl-down-70-points/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I Brought My LDL (“Bad”) Cholesterol Down 70 Points in 3 Months" /><published>2024-01-06T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/01/06/ldl-down-70-points</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/01/06/ldl-down-70-points/"><![CDATA[<nav id="TOC" role="doc-toc">
  <a href="/">Home</a><br>
  <strong>Contents</strong><label for="contents">⊕</label>
  <input type="checkbox" id="contents">
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#some-context" id="toc-some-context">Some
  Context</a></li>
  <li><a href="#introduction"
  id="toc-introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#tldr-what-actually-worked"
  id="toc-tldr-what-actually-worked">TL;DR — What Actually
  Worked</a></li>
  <li><a href="#foods-i-ate-almost-every-day"
  id="toc-foods-i-ate-almost-every-day">Foods I Ate <em>Almost Every
  Day</em></a>
  <ul>
  <li><a href="#smoothie-ingredients"
  id="toc-smoothie-ingredients">Smoothie ingredients</a></li>
  <li><a href="#why-psyllium" id="toc-why-psyllium">Why
  psyllium?</a></li>
  </ul></li>
  <li><a href="#typical-dinners" id="toc-typical-dinners">Typical
  Dinners</a></li>
  <li><a href="#cheat-meals" id="toc-cheat-meals">Cheat Meals</a></li>
  <li><a href="#foods-i-missed-couldnt-find-good-substitutes"
  id="toc-foods-i-missed-couldnt-find-good-substitutes">Foods I Missed
  (Couldn’t Find Good Substitutes)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#exercise" id="toc-exercise">Exercise</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
  <li><a href="#whats-next" id="toc-whats-next">What’s Next</a></li>
  </ul>
</nav>

<main>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Disclaimer — I’m <strong>not</strong> a doctor. This is a sample
size of one. Always talk to your own physician before changing diet,
exercise, or medication.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<hr />
<h2 id="some-context">Some Context</h2>
<ul>
<li>39-year-old South Asian male<br />
</li>
<li>Starting weight ≈ 160 lb (72 kg)<br />
</li>
<li>Target daily intake ≈ 1,700 kcal (per TDEE calculator)</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>On <strong>28 Sep 2023</strong> my lipid panel showed:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Total cholesterol:</strong> 258 mg/dL<br />
</li>
<li><strong>LDL-C:</strong> 175 mg/dL</li>
</ul>
<p>That Sunday my doctor phoned to recommend starting a statin
<strong>immediately</strong>.<br />
I asked for three months to try dietary changes first—right through the
holidays.</p>
<p>Three months later (<strong>5 Jan 2024</strong>) the repeat panel
read:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Marker</th>
<th>28 Sep 2023</th>
<th>5 Jan 2024</th>
<th>Change</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Total Cholesterol</td>
<td>258</td>
<td><strong>178</strong></td>
<td>−80</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>LDL-C</td>
<td>175</td>
<td><strong>105</strong></td>
<td>−70</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<!-- image total-cholesterol-chart.png -->
<!-- image ldl-chart.png -->
<hr />
<h2 id="tldr-what-actually-worked">TL;DR — What Actually Worked</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Fiber ↑</strong> — ≈ 40 g /day (half soluble, half
insoluble)<br />
</li>
<li><strong>Saturated fat ↓</strong><br />
</li>
<li>Protein kept ≥ 100 g /day to maintain satiety and lean mass</li>
</ol>
<p>I had previously obsessed over protein and ignored fiber; this flip
made the difference.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="foods-i-ate-almost-every-day">Foods I Ate <em>Almost Every
Day</em></h2>
<table>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 15%" />
<col style="width: 43%" />
<col style="width: 41%" />
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Item</th>
<th>Typical Portion</th>
<th>Notes / macros</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>1 % milk chai latte</strong></td>
<td>8 oz 1 % milk + 1.5 Tbsp loose chai + 8 crushed cardamom pods</td>
<td><em>P</em>: 9 g, <em>C</em>: 15 g, <em>F</em>: 2.5 g, SatFat 1.5
g</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Black coffee</strong></td>
<td>10 oz pourover</td>
<td>zero-cal pick-me-up</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Protein + fiber smoothie</strong></td>
<td>see ingredients below</td>
<td><em>P</em>: 45 g, <em>F</em>: 11 g, Fiber ≈ 22 g</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Greek yogurt + blueberries</strong></td>
<td>1 cup yogurt + 100 g berries</td>
<td><em>P</em>: 22 g, Fiber 2 g</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Apple and/or pear</strong></td>
<td>1 medium</td>
<td>Fiber ≈ 5 g</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td><strong>Stovetop popcorn</strong></td>
<td>¼ cup kernels</td>
<td>Fiber 10 g, <em>P</em>: 8 g</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td><strong>Eggs</strong></td>
<td>2 large</td>
<td>SatFat 3 g</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3 id="smoothie-ingredients">Smoothie ingredients</h3>
<ul>
<li>8 oz unsweetened soy milk<br />
</li>
<li>30 g Gold Standard whey<br />
</li>
<li>12 g chia seeds (soaked)<br />
</li>
<li>8 g psyllium husk<br />
</li>
<li>16 g peanut-butter powder<br />
</li>
<li>5 g cinnamon<br />
</li>
<li>5 g unsweetened cocoa</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="why-psyllium">Why psyllium?</h3>
<p>Psyllium husk is mostly <strong>soluble</strong> fiber, which forms a
gel in the gut and helps pull LDL out of circulation.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="typical-dinners">Typical Dinners</h2>
<ul>
<li>Indian yellow curry<br />
</li>
<li>Wild salmon + rice + edamame<br />
</li>
<li>Pan-fried scallops<br />
</li>
<li>Indian <strong>daal</strong> (often with extra yogurt)<br />
</li>
<li>Cottage-cheese waffles / pancakes<br />
</li>
<li><em>Sooji</em> (semolina) pancakes<br />
</li>
<li>Korean-flavored tofu stir-fry</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h2 id="cheat-meals">Cheat Meals</h2>
<p>I tried to avoid true cheat meals, but my sweet-tooth workaround was
<strong>cottage-cheese waffles</strong>—high protein, low sat-fat, and
you <em>can’t taste</em> the cottage cheese.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="foods-i-missed-couldnt-find-good-substitutes">Foods I Missed
(Couldn’t Find Good Substitutes)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Pizza (the cheese!)<br />
</li>
<li>Chocolate<br />
</li>
<li>Donuts<br />
</li>
<li>Butter-heavy cookies &amp; pastries</li>
</ul>
<p>Every “healthy” version I tried tasted like cardboard; I chose
abstinence over disappointment.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="exercise">Exercise</h2>
<ul>
<li>≈ 10 000 steps/day (light walking burns a few hundred kcal)<br />
</li>
<li>Minimal weights or HIIT—lots of false starts here. I could improve
this phase.</li>
</ul>
<hr />
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>These three months accomplished:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Fiber</strong> ∼ 40 g/day<br />
</li>
<li><strong>Sat fat</strong> kept low<br />
</li>
<li><strong>Protein</strong> &gt; 100 g/day</li>
</ul>
<p>Body weight settled at <strong>147 lb</strong> and I feel noticeably
better.</p>
<hr />
<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next</h2>
<ul>
<li>Maintain high fiber + protein<br />
</li>
<li>Loosen cheat days (slightly higher sat-fat)<br />
</li>
<li>Ramp up cardio &amp; consistent weight training</li>
</ul>
<p>My hunch: fiber alone did most of the LDL-lowering heavy-lifting.
Time will tell whether LDL stays low once I re-introduce moderate
sat-fat.</p>
<hr />
<p><em>Questions?</em> Email
<strong>neeraj.kapoor@learntobe.org</strong>—always happy to chat.</p>
</main>]]></content><author><name>Neeraj</name></author><category term="health" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[← Return home Disclaimer — I’m not a doctor. This is a sample size of one. Always talk to your own physician before changing diet, exercise, or medication.]]></summary></entry></feed>